okay so I guess we're there so let's get
started so uh well gosh what an
influence John John had in my life uh
there I was a fledgling philosopher
trying to uh interested in in
mathematics
and and he'd gone through his writings
in the in the Long Way a long time ago
in the 1990s gave me the confidence to
think that you you could get access to
the Forefront of of mathematical and
phys scientific knowledge
through his writings I mean what gosh
what a what a joy that was to to engage
with his writings back at that time huge
influence on me and you know a bunch of
people will know that we started a Blog
together a while ago we had a lot of
conversations over over a great many
years
so it's great pleasure to have him speak
to us here today on on the play category
Theory so thank you John
well thanks very much thanks for
inviting me here and uh the influence
was reciprocal uh it's really
exciting to think that what one is doing
in mathematics could actually be
interesting to a philosopher so that uh
one isn't just like fiddling around with
obscure equations
uh so I want to talk about applied
category Theory which is the latest turn
in this game
uh and
I'll talk more about the history of the
subject and what people are trying to do
then
uh any mathematics per se
I've given lots of talks about the
mathematics and so if all the people who
I'll be
uh referring to here so it's certainly
easy to click on any of the links in my
slides and get into the actual
mathematics but I'll try to not say
as much about that as I sometimes do
so
we often have this picture of different
uh
disciplines or subject areas talking to
their neighbors and information flowing
between pure math which is at some very
abstract and
uh to say the business World which is
maybe at the very concrete end in stages
with each
discipline talking mainly to its
neighbors so pure mathematicians talk to
applied mathematicians they give
suggestions to applied mathematicians
and they find out about problems from
applied mathematicians
and learn techniques from applied
mathematicians and similarly for each
link down the chain with each uh
discipline talking to its neighbors and
in this model which of course is very
oversimplified and and you can easily
find a lot of
faults in it uh in this model we could
think of category Theory as the purest
of pure some super pure mathematics that
only can talk to mathematicians who then
relay their insights down the chain to
the other more practical subjects
um
I think that's what a lot of people
implicitly feel about category Theory or
at least used to uh and so when people
started talking about applied category
Theory people laughed because it sounds
like an oxymoron it just goes completely
against this picture here
however I think this picture is
inaccurate
um
for one thing a very important fact is
that starting maybe around 1980 or so it
became clear that computer science
really cuts across this traditional flow
of information computer science
interacts
almost directly with every single
piece of this chain
computer science has a big relation to
category Theory which I'll explain but
it also has a huge relation to other
aspects of
pure mathematics
and Applied Mathematics and so on down
to business so business
es will need to keep abreast of
developments in computer science and so
on basically
we now communicate and think with the
help of these machines called computers
that we have devised to help us and and
they changed the whole game at every
single step of the way
now I have this crazy idea that maybe
category Theory actually really should
be thought of in a somewhat similar way
as interacting with all the different
links in the chain from the pure end to
the applied end rather than being tucked
away at the super pure end of the
spectrum now at first it seems
ridiculous and are laughable I mean for
starters category theory is sort of
nothing compared to computer science
everybody's walking around carrying cell
phones
nobody has even heard of categories by
comparison so category two is an ant
compared to the elephant of computer
science
however I'm thinking about what could be
not what yet is and secondly
when you think about how computers have
unified the whole chain
it's done so by means of the internet
which is an enormous Network
and category Theory isn't nothing if not
the mathematics of of networks or the
science of networks it's other things
too I shouldn't have said it quite that
way I mean it's it is the science of
networks but it does many other things
too uh
so so to really devise
good methods of getting computers to do
what we want
you need a way to think about them and I
think category theory is one of the
important ways to think about them
so you may think this is
ridiculous still because for example if
category theory was talking directly to
business
you'd expect that people would be going
into business during category Theory or
something like that setting up category
Theory businesses that sounds sort of
silly but in fact it's true so in fact
people are setting up category Theory
businesses and that's part of the kind
of thing I want to talk about I want to
talk about how category theory is now
being used at all
uh steps along the Spectrum and for that
reason my talk will be less focused on
the math than on the history of how
category Theory became applied giving
you a flavor of how it's being applied
and pointing out some of the challenges
that show up
um uh before I dive in I should say that
this history is going to be extremely
self-centered I'm not really in a
position to write a good or talk about a
good history of
category Theory so hopefully someone who
eventually tries to write a history of
Applied category Theory we'll listen to
this talk and fold it in as one data
point uh I'll talk about a lot of people
but I will also leave out a lot of
people and I really apologize to all the
people whose work on applied category
Theory I'm not mentioning
there's just no way for me to do a fair
treatment of this big subject
okay so I'll start arbitrarily in 1963
when Bill of beer introduced a concept
called frontorial semantics
so it's a very general concept where
you have a category
that describes uh syntax describes ways
of writing things down
and then
describe the process of interpreting
those expressions or giving a meaning to
those expressions the functor
so from the functor will send
expressions
to their meanings but a crucial aspect
of this whole setup is that there's not
one god-given functor F that does this
you can choose various functors from the
category C to various other categories
key
uh because they're different ways to
assign meanings to expressions and that
flexibility is very important
and it became important in computer
science
so for example there's a
a nice there's a way to think about it
where exceptionally well behaved
programming language may give a category
where you think of the objects as types
or data types we've already heard about
that idea so types x y z Etc and then
amorphism between objects like amorphism
f from X to Y we think of it as a
program that accepts data of Type X is
input and outputs data of type y
and then the fact that you can compose
morphisms
uh tells you that you can hook up two
programs to get a bigger program or the
output of the first
program becomes the input of the second
and like that
that combination that is a program in
itself
so I could say that like the
relationship between the Lambda calculus
which is sort of an idealized
programming language simplified
programming language and Cartesian
closed categories uh understood by
Lambic is an example of this Paradigm of
using functorial semantics for uh
for computer science but here I'm only
so far talked about the category C I
haven't talked about the uh the functor
so what the functor could do well we
could for example take a functor from
our category to the category of sets
not each data type X to a set and that
would be the set of possible values of
the of that data so like you could have
a data type like real numbers and then
definitely map it to the actual set of
real numbers
uh and then each program gets mapped
ideally to a function and the key factor
of a functor is that it preserves
composition so that composing programs
would compose the would give rise to
composing the functions they compute and
the identity
program which does nothing at all
you interpreted via this functor F it
gives you the identity function which
does nothing at all on a set
so that's a that's a paradigm that
became important in theoretical computer
science I wouldn't say that most uh
computer scientists know or care about
funtorial synaptics but in a certain
community of the more mathematical uh
theoretical computer scientists this
idea has become quite important
and there are certain languages like
Haskell for example and others that that
really take advantage of this Viewpoint
in particular Haskell uses a category
theoretic construct called moonads which
has sent many uh generations of young
computer scientists running for for help
from a category theorists to try to
figure out what a monad is I don't want
to explain what a Monet is it's a
category theoretic construct which like
many other constructs become important
when you start thinking about
programming in this punctorial synaptics
way
but in the 1980s something very
different happened uh particle
physicists realized that any Quantum
field Theory specifies a category and
now the objects are roughly speaking
collections of particles and the
morphisms are roughly speaking ways for
particles to interact and turn into
other particles and in fact Feynman Drew
pictures called Feynman diagrams
for describing how particles interact
with each other this was a bold move
because although it seems very intuitive
here you have a proton and an
anti-proton coming in from the left and
then they Collide and all sorts of other
particles shoot out
uh in reality particles are not little
dots moving along little straight lines
quantum mechanics says that particles
are are wave like in character so when
Feynman introduced this pictorial
language he got a lot of opposition from
older Quantum physicists like
heisenbergen and Bohr and yet it turned
out Feynman was correct in doing this
what finally diagrams actually are later
became clear much later is there
pictures of morphisms in specific
categories and each individual Quantum
field Theory gives a category and then
that determines what allowed find the
diagrams you can write so if you have a
theory that
doesn't have quarks in it you're not
allowed to write this q line for for
quark
um
and then what do you do with these
pictures Well you your goal in in
particle physics is to compute a bunch
of numbers like what's the probability
that if I smack two particles into each
other that some other particle shoots
out so for calculating numbers we need
uh to interpret our assignment diagram
that is in the functorial semantics
attitude we need to functor from our
category to some other category which
assigns meaning to the finding diagrams
in this category we could take to be the
category of Hobart spaces a widely loved
mathematical structure in quantum
mechanics and so then it will this
function will turn any Feynman diagram
into amorphism in the category of
Hilbert's faces and that's called a
linear operator between Hilbert spaces
and so you can look at what physicists
are doing with Feynman diagrams uh as
basically using them as a syntax which
they then apply the semantics to to then
grind out numbers
now Feynman probably would have laughed
at this whole business because he knew
what he was doing he didn't need any
category theorists to tell them what
what he was doing but by the 1980s
particle physics had become elaborate
enough and deeply connected with enough
pure mathematics that this attitude of
thinking of
upon field theory in terms of functorial
semantics became a really profitable
attitude you could do things with
category theory that particle physicists
were struggling to do without category
Theory and so it helped
and this led to a whole line of work uh
trying to relate category Theory to
quantum mechanics
and in 2004 Samson abramski and Bob
kirka wrote a very influential paper
showing that a certain Quantum process
that goes by the name quantum
teleportation
and also other
processes could be understood using
category Theory and using diagrams that
resemble find the diagrams but here the
edges in these diagrams which now I
guess we're reading from top to bottom
rather than across the edges are not
describing Elementary particles but just
states of an arbitrary
Quantum system so it could be an
electron or it could be some larger
system and I don't want to try to
explain this in detail but there are but
these are pictures of morphisms in some
category
and they're equal to each other and
these morphisms describe some process
where one participant always is called
Alice in cryptography uh communicates a
message to another participant it's
called Bob
and in quantum teleportation
you have the superficial appearance that
you're communicating uh faster than
light
but in fact what's really going on is
that you've laid the ground for the
communication by some classical process
that has already transferred some
information and then the rest of the
information uh is transferred on the
basis of that
in any event quantum teleportation was a
sort of magical wonderful thing that you
can do in quantum mechanics and this
gave a kind of category theoretic
theoretic account for how it how it's
working
and that was quite exciting to people
because it took the quantum applications
of category Theory out of the realm of
elementary particle physics and into a
new realm that was developing which is
quantum information Theory or Quantum
computation
which has the potential for being a
quite practical thing and indeed already
a Quantum cryptography is a is is it is
used
so on the basis of this and other work
and also on the basis I should say over
a huge amount of Charisma Bob Kirker and
Samson abramsky
built a huge group of people at Oxford
sometimes called the quantum group
working on category Theory the
foundations of quantum physics and
Quantum computation one interesting
thing about this enormous group here is
that it's in the computer science
department so not a mathematics
Department not even a physics department
but a computer science department here's
Samson abrovsky here and here's Bob
kirka looking sort of disreputable over
on the edge that's completely
intentional he's like that and here are
many many people including I see Jules
Hedges who has mentioned uh
in the previous talk that you were
example categorical cybernetics
um so Circa and co-authors developed
this diagrammatic method for explaining
quantum physics
and they eventually decided it would be
very good to write a textbook on this
and so here's one of the two textbooks
that Bob kruka helped write on pictorial
methods of understanding quantum physics
and the one interesting thing about this
book so first of all I recommend this
book if you're interested in learning
category Theory from a unorthodox and
sort of easier
approach than the conventional one
because it's very pictorial uh but I
mentioned it because part of what what
you wound up doing is hiding the
category theory in the sense that you
don't run around saying category and
functor and all sorts of other jargon
like that a lot instead you draw
pictures of processes and you explain
these pictures in a Hands-On way and you
explain how you can stick one picture
onto the other which is composing
morphisms but you don't say the word
composing morphisms necessarily because
you don't need to
uh and this is one of a generation I
should say a new generation of category
Theory textbooks that are part of the
applied category Theory movement so if a
category theory is going to reach
directly to many different communities
at different stages of the knowledge
chain that I drew at the top of the talk
uh it means that you can't force people
to first become mathematicians before
they then start doing things with
category Theory the traditional approach
to category Theory treats category
theories like some finishing school that
you engage in after you've already
learned abstract algebra and this and
that and algebraic topology and so on
that's just too onerous a path to
category theory if you're trying to get
a computer scientists much less business
people to get some inkling of category
Theory and it's not really necessary to
take that elaborate route because
category 30 is something so fundamental
that it can be explained more directly I
especially recommend Eugenia Chang's
book The Joy of abstraction which is a
really wonderful introduction to
category theory for people who have not
had much prior exposure to mathematics
at all and it goes all the way up to the
Oneida embedding theorem
thank you
so in 2021 Perka actually left Oxford
University and he became the chief
scientist of a company called Continuum
which uses category theory for Quantum
Computing and also natural language
processing
this is a picture of him on the
Continuum web page
as you can see he's trying to quite hard
not to fall into the stereotypical
academic image here he's a great guy by
the way you shouldn't mind me teasing
him like this uh
I think though that it is important it's
having people with personalities who are
willing to break out of the
stereotypical mold of
a
math professor is important in this
whole category Theory
application movement
uh I should say that there's a lot of
interaction between
Quantum Computing ideas and natural
language processing ideas which I won't
really have time to get into
uh to some extent they were visible in
the last talk but if you want a real
emphasis on the natural language
processing aspect The Works of uh Tai
Denae Bradley are very good she's
another
newer explainer of category Theory it's
a non-category theorists and she is also
working uh in a company that
uses Quantum methods and categorical
methods for natural language processing
but Ontario semantics is extremely
General so we it's not just applicable
to the topics that I've already
mentioned so in lots of areas of Science
and Engineering people use a syntax
where
you you draw diagrams
and then a synaptics where you convert
those diagrams into math which is very
often the systems of
differential equations you're describing
how things change in time you're
describing dynamical systems uh
so you use differential equations
but the interesting part is that hooking
up
diagrams to each other is actually
composing morphisms in a category
and the fact that you're
you're working with frontorial semantics
says that when you compose
those morphisms in the syntax category
your functor
will map it the resulting composite to
the composite of the two systems of
differential equations that each picture
separately is mapped to so in other
words there's another category lurking
around here where the morphisms are
actually systems of differential
equations
systems of differential equations with
some specified inputs and outputs to
surface
as the source and target of your
morphism here are some different
pictures you've seen a bunch of these
types of pictures I hope so electrical
circuit diagrams are are one of the
earliest and very widely used
um
this thing here is a called a petri net
and it's a petri nut of a particular
model for the AIDS
virus and its interaction with blood
cells infection of of white blood cells
this here is a very small uh diagram in
the subject of control theory where you
have some process in an industrial plant
that you're trying to keep under control
and so you take feedback you read off
information from that process and you
use it to feedback
affect the the process itself to keep it
on track I mean the very simplest
example here would be like a thermostat
but in in industrial chemistry they
become much more elaborate
and so there's a whole diagrammatic
language of control theory that you can
read about in textbooks on that subject
and this is a
little diagram of some molecules in
molecular biology molecular biology or
biochemistry they have so many different
diagram languages that in fact they've
set up a committee on to standardize the
diagram languages so that people reading
different biochemistry papers can look
at the diagrams and not have to be
explained each time what the diagrams
mean but it's sufficiently Baroque that
they uh that the committee wound up
choosing three different diagram
languages because they they need
multiple languages to describe different
things they're interested in
so these are very widespread and the
people in these different subjects don't
think of what they're doing here as
category Theory they don't think of it
as mathematics they think of it as this
is the stuff we draw
to understand the differential equations
that you can convert these pictures into
the equations of the math but these
pictures are our own private little
trick for understanding what's going on
but I claim that these pictures are
actually also mathematics and they're
these diagrams are morphisms in various
categories which are using functorial
synaptics to convert to differential
equations
like
excited that had to be true and I wanted
to work out the details
around 2012 so I asked
Brendan Fawn who eventually became my
grad student to
tackle what I thought would be a very
good first example namely electrical
circuits
because everybody knows about electrical
circuits and the mathematics of them is
in substance very well understood
linear electrical circuits for example
made out of just resistors or maybe
capacitors and inductors as well
um
I asked them to create and study a
category having open electrical circuits
as morphism so these are electrical
circuits which have certain things
hanging out which serves as inputs and
outputs I think in the last part they
are called cilia so these are just these
dots here
um so it took forever to do it so it
seemed but it turned out that what he
was doing was not just answering the
question that I asked but in fact
uh answering a much more general
question he invented a general theory
which he called decorated Coast bands
for handling this problem but also all
the other problems that I described that
is essentially all the other kinds of
diagram languages
all right showed can be understood using
the theory of decorated co-spans
although the details have to be
individually worked out in each case
this decorated coastband formalism is a
is a recipe for getting categories of
this General sort and so naturally it
did take him a while to do a good job of
it and he finished his thesis on it in
2016. I won't attempt to explain
decorated post bands any more than I
just have I've given lots of talks on
decorating post bands and you can see on
YouTube me giving talks about them if
you're interested I just want to mention
one little thing is that well first of
all here's Brennan Fong and here's
another student of mine Blake Pollard
who together with Brendan applied this
theory of decorated close bands to the
second example that we tackled which was
Markov processes
did a lot of work on Markov processes
uh and another thing I want to mention
is that uh Brendan went to
get his PhD at Oxford so he was in the
enormous group that I mentioned
and I believe Kirko is his de facto it
was his day jury advisor but in fact I
was the the de facto advisor telling you
important to Brendan about this this
problem uh and so nonetheless it's
really important that this large body of
people that uh at uh
at Oxford is is spreading across the
world doing many things and Brendan is
one of them
so after doing this doing his PhD uh
Brendan went to MIT in 2016 to work as a
postdoc with David spiveak so spivack is
another very important figure in applied
category Theory so among other things he
had helped to create a language for
databases called functorial query
language
which has now become the basis of a
company called Connexus AI with Ryan
wisniewsky as a as a head of that
company but David Spivak also involved
this
approach the databases really relies
heavily on functorial semantics so the
idea is the database schema is
is an object in some category and then
by a functor you can map it to a sort of
populated or inhabited database schema
where where the the
your table of is actually filled with
entries you can imagine like taking a
spreadsheet and actually typing in the
entries that's one possible uh
interpretation of of the abstract
database that has not yet been
interpreted with with specific people's
names and numbers
uh
and in 2014 David wrote a textbook on
this idea and others called category
theory for the Sciences so I also highly
recommend this as yet another uh of this
new generation of category Theory
textbooks let's try to reach out beyond
the traditional confines of the category
Theory community
of Highly pure mathematicians toward
other audiences
and in 2010 2018 uh Brendan Fong and
David Spivak wrote another textbook
explicitly on applied category Theory
which is uh fondly called seven sketches
but its actual title is here earns lager
uh emphasizing the principle of
compositionality in many guises and they
taught a course on it which you can see
on YouTube if you click on this link in
my slides and the textbook is also
available for free on the archive as
well as
for purchase
and I'm mentioning this stuff about
things being available online for free
partially because when you're trying to
reach out
of the
pure math realm into the rest of the
world and teach the rest of the world
category Theory you quickly realize that
making things easily available for free
is going to speed up the process a lot
and so I think there's a general
commitment so far on the part of a lot
of Applied category theorists to make
things open source and uh easy to get at
now in 2018 my graduate student Kenny
corser there and I came up with
structured Coast Fans which is a simpler
alternative to decorated Coast bands
turns out to be not quite as flexible as
decorated Coast Fans but in many cases
either formalism works and in those
cases I'd say structured co-spans are
simpler in 2020 Christina vasilicopolu
who's standing to the left there uh
helped us understand how decorated and
structured Coast bands are related for a
while I thought structured Coast Fans
would replace decorated Coast Fans but
it turns out we we now see that they
can't cover quite as much territory and
that we really need decorated co-spans
in some case cases so the full story is
somewhat elaborate right now uh I've
given talks about that but it's it's
actually very pretty
so by now structured and decorated Coast
Fans have been used to study open
systems of many kinds so by open systems
I mean systems that have loose ends that
are meaning systems that are amorphisms
in a category that you can stick
together or compose to get bigger
systems and
where open graphs are just a simply a
graph with Loose Ends it's very
combinatorial structure that's a very
simple example open Petri Nets is a more
useful example here's a picture of a an
open Petri net where you have uh
things describing up they're called
called places that could represent like
populations of different kinds of
chemicals or organisms and then you have
these blue boxes called transitions
which describe how things can come out
of various places and turn into things
of other kinds
um if you attach numbers to these
transitions
uh describing the rate at which the
transition tends to occur you get
something called a open Petri net with
rates or maybe an open chemical reaction
network with rates uh
and my student Blake Pollard worked on
those open electrical circuits I've
mentioned open Markov processes I
mentioned open dynamical systems those
at the systems of differential equations
interpreted as morphisms in some
category
so there are papers on all of these and
if you click on these Brown things
you'll get to those papers
so at a certain point I thought that
maybe someday all of this would lead to
some unified language of the Sciences
and my ambition
which seems very limited in retrospect
was that by
interacting with Scientists maybe
eventually
this unified language would help
scientists in one discipline talk to
scientists in another discipline and
share tricks of various sorts
but then something quite different
happened which is much more exciting in
my mind namely in 2019
James Fairbanks is an engineer and Evan
Patterson who had statistics
PhD began developing a computer system
called algebraic Julia
for it's a system for high performance
scientific computing
built on the language called Julia
which is designed for crunching numbers
really fast
but
algebraic Julia lets you program it
using constructs from category Theory so
in algebraic Julia you can talk about
categories functors and all these other
things that category theorists like to
talk about and write your programs using
those contents so it's a very very high
level system but coupled to the raw
computational power of algebraic Julia
so now we're attractive revolutionize
scientific Computing in this way
and in 2020
Evan implemented structured co-spans in
algebraic Julia
and then using this system uh for the
example of open Tech units he and Mika
halter
reconstructed some of a covid-19 model
which was currently being used by the UK
government
so the UK government had a very
elaborate model of covid-19 with many
populations of different people with
different conditions possibly living in
different locations Etc uh and then I
guess sorry the populations of these
orange boxes and able to turn into other
kinds of people via these transitions in
blue
the
whole model is much larger than this
this is just a tiny fraction of it and
what
they wanted to demonstrate was that you
could build the whole model by building
smaller models and pieces and then
subsequently sticking together those
pieces
which is in fact something that had not
been done before models were sort of had
to be constructed in whole cloth by
essentially by one person keeping track
of the whole thing
but this is a new approach compositional
epidemiology and so it attracted the
attention of some epidemiologists
especially since covid-19 is a very live
issue at the time
then in a different direction in 2021
Brendan Fong and David Spivak who had
been remembered over at MIT decided to
quit traditional Academia and start
their own Institute called the topless
Institute in downtown Berkeley
it's an Institute for Applied
Mathematics
but with a heavy slant on applied
category Theory
and they hired a number of people
including Evan Patterson and also Sophie
libkin who's here who will appear later
in the story
and it's a real real incubator for our
ideas on a flight category Theory now
and so this is another one of the
sociological moves that I had to be made
I think to bring applied category Theory
forward I recommended Brendan not try to
start an Institute right after his first
postdoc but luckily he was much braver
than I would ever be and he went ahead
and did it and it's quite successful now
so in 2022
Sophie Lipkin Mika halter Evan Patterson
James Fairbanks and another person I
haven't mentioned Andrew boss used
algebraic Julia to systematically
build models of epidemia
epidemiology using open Petri Nets with
rates so here are some open Petri Nets
the rates that is in the number data is
not being shown here and here they're
being stuck together to form a larger
open Petri net the way that they're
being stuck together you'll notice is
not end to end this is not the normal
end-to-end composition that you see in a
category this is something a little bit
more General
we're sticking them together using a
trick called an operand so operatic
composition is one of the things that
they Incorporated in their algebraic
Jewelers software which is
this was done this previous work was
done in a slightly at hot basis but but
this really used operats in the
systematic way
and then in 2022 also
another team of people including myself
used to algebraic Julia to create
software for building models of
epidemiology using another style of
diagrams called open Stock flow diagrams
well stock flow diagrams but we're
making them open so here are some of
those kind of diagrams being stuck
together in an operatic style that is
not end to end but sort of gluing them
all together to form a bigger model
so part of the point here is that when
we started talking to actual
epidemiologists
we applied category theorists learned
more about how they actually want to do
their models and they didn't really want
to do their models using pet units
primarily they wanted to use a different
technique that they considered congenial
called stock flow diagrams
um so in fact there's a community of
epidemiologists who use stock flow
diagrams to model the spread of disease
and it includes my co-authors Nathaniel
Osgood and his grad student xiaoyen Lee
and one crucial fact is that they did
covid modeling for the government of
Canada so they were requested by the
government of Canada to set up covid
models for the a number of different
provinces
and in the process they gained a lot of
experience uh with stock flow models
they already had a lot of experience and
they wouldn't have been asked to do it
but they gained a lot more experience
and they learned some of the problems of
the existing technology
this is a beautiful thing about stock
flow diagrams which is that with a
little bit of just a little bit of
training you can read them and you can
understand what they're talking about so
a fellow named Hoffman has pushed the
idea of community-based modeling where
you go to a community that has some
problem like a disease or some other
type of problem and you help model it
and you model it by drawing stock flow
diagrams which here are hanging on the
wall in a in a room in rural India
and that people can
look at those diagrams and comment on
them and help you improve the model
because these people the the local
people they will have the knowledge of
what's actually going on that the you
the modeler who just flew in from from
Oxford or wherever may not have and here
we see a woman here looking at the
picture on the wall and this is actually
from a story where this woman noticed
that some ingredient was being left out
of the model uh that these Village
Elders hadn't known about or had thought
about and so she helped fix the model
so that's the example of what you can do
and you'll notice that none of the
people in this story here had to know
category Theory but they were in fact uh
drawing morphisms in the category on the
notes to themselves
now most stock flow modeling in the
commercial level or the hype or the
government level is done using a piece
of software called any logic which is
very powerful but it has several big
problems
it doesn't let you compose models it
lets you make a model but it doesn't let
you take a bunch of models and stick
them together
it doesn't separate syntax from
semantics it only has one semantics
namely the differential equation
semantics which is the most important
semantics but there are others that you
would like
it has no support for what's called
stratifying models that term was very
confusing to me it's sort of charging in
on this community what it means is
taking a model and splitting One stock
one type of group of people into several
stocks so for example you might have a
simple model and then you may say oh we
should subdivide people according to age
groups because older people who get the
disease more more than younger people or
something like that and you would like
your software to make it easy to to do
that
um it had no support for collaboratively
building models it's basically one
person as the software and they make the
model they could talk to other people
but they're the one who's building the
model
and it's not free it's commercial piece
of software and it's not open source so
people can't get in there and modify it
and improve it
our new work and to fix all these
problems and I could say we're well on
the way to fixing all these problems
so the reason it's so important to
produce models is that the models that
get actually used in the real world are
immensely complex so here's a picture of
Osgood and Lee's covid model this is a
page in any logic the software this is
the whole model as you can see it's an
enormous web of of stocks and flows and
such and you you really would prefer
actually not to have to deal with this
whole entity at at once you prefer to
have it be thought of as being made up
out of smaller pieces because mentally
it is made up out of smaller pieces uh
but but that's not captured by the the
software unfortunately any logic just
doesn't do that for you
so we've not created software that does
that it supports compositional modeling
with the stock flow diagrams so it's
called stock flow and if you click on
this link you'll go to GitHub which is
where computer programmers keep their
open source software so you can get
download the software
and so it lets you create and compose
open Stock flow diagrams and lets you
stratify them that is subdivide stocks
into smaller stocks for those of you who
like category Theory I'll mention that
that's done using a technique called
pullbacks in category Theory it lets you
choose among several different semantics
functors so one of which is the
differential equation semantics
uh and of course it lets you solve the
differential equations once you get them
and then Nate Osgood and another student
of his Eric redika went further and made
a graphical user interface for stock
flow so stock flow is written in this
programming language called algebraic
Julia to interact with it you needed to
know algebraic Julia
but this graphical inner graphical user
interface called Model collab it runs on
a browser and you manipulate the the
model by actually dragging and dropping
little boxes and drawing little edges
between boxes
still
uh and because it runs on multiple
browsers teams of different people
located in different locations can a lot
can collaborate to build stock flow
diagrams so I could build my piece you
could build your piece we could both
save them they'd be saved on the on the
cloud and I see there's this little
thing called Cloud here uh that that's
not what it is actually for them sorry
that's a mistake uh but but you can you
can say it's gonna laugh at that
um actually clouds are these little
funny things here
uh but you can say you can save your
models on the uh on the internet and so
that other people in different locations
can access them and then glue them
together to form larger models
so in the goal to really apply
mathematics there are many levels
because the next step is to actually
train epidemiologists to use model
collab so we have some things going for
us so first of all eight Osgood runs
regular training sessions which goes by
the Quasi militaristic terminology
favored in computer science of boot
camps because they're supposed to be
intense so it runs boot camps on
epidemiological modeling so he is
beginning to teach people model cloud
second no understanding of category
Theory or the programming language Julia
is required to use model collab so it's
really crucial when you're applying
category three that you can ultimately
Black Box the category theory in it so
that people do not explicitly need to
know it to use what you're creating
although they may be using it in some
kind of implicit way
uh and third it's free while any logic
you have to pay for which should
ultimately be an advantage
but I should still say it will take a
lot of work because when you have a
generation of modelers trying to use any
logic this new paradigm is not so easy
to shape
so as I just already said applying
mathematics takes many steps and as I've
moved from being more of a pure
mathematician towards a bit more at
least some some days of the week of an
applied mathematician I realize how easy
peer mathematicians have it you just
write a paper you explain your idea you
throw it out there and you hope that
somebody reads it but when you're trying
to actually carry out the full
application of an idea you have to
interact with many people with many
skills persuade many different
communities that what you're doing is
actually worth doing and it's much more
elaborate but I should also say very
satisfying endeavor
laughs so I'll conclude by saying that
applied category theory is interesting
in in many ways some of which I hope
will be interesting to philosophers
uh so
some of these ways are separate from
sort of the core mathematical ideas so
one thing as I hope I've Illustrated
here
by my somewhat self-centered history is
that it requires new forms of
communication and collaboration because
they're talking to new types of people
and luckily uh
these are starting to come into
existence so there's an annual
applied category Theory conference
that's first started in 2018
uh run that time by Brendan Fong and
some of his other young friends
another is a journal so there's a
journal
called compositionality which is again
started by Brandon falling in some of
his
collaborators and friends this is an
open access free to publish free to read
Journal of Applied category Theory which
I recommend to your attention
and another is called the category
Theory Community server which is sort of
like a a chat site or a discussion site
for Applied category Theory actually for
all category three but it has a lot of
Applied category theorists there uh this
was initiated by my grad student
Christian Williams
and so these are different ways for
category theorists to start talking to
other kinds of people people who want to
might want to apply category Theory or
learn category three and I hope that
these catalyze the the
process done
trying to outline here
another thing is that category Theory
raises ethical issues in ways that
category theorists aren't used to
pure mathematicians tend to feel
themselves somewhat insulated from a lot
of ethical issues because
what although their math make it used
for all sorts of purposes
they don't consider themselves
particularly responsible for how their
mathematics gets used because it's so
abstracted they sort of can blame
someone else for understanding it and
doing something with it
um
but when you start doing uh explicitly
applied to category theory that sort of
veil of uh protection is is ripped open
and you see that what you're doing may
have a fairly immediate effect
so for example the biggest funder of
research on applied category theory is
currently the US military right now
and also a lot of Applied category
theory is being used for artificial
intelligence or machine learning or
large language models or so on
so I'm not saying that those are
necessarily bad things I'm saying that
those are things that definitely raise
serious ethical issues
and so I'm worried about the danger that
applied category Theory will wind up
merely intensifying
deal already existing
patterns in society that is it will only
make the richest and most powerful
people even richer and more powerful
I would prefer it if applied category
Theory could do something really
different really new this is one reason
why I've tried to focus on epidemiology
which is a little bit different than
than some of the other
uh applications of course even at the
demiology ultimately feeds into the
healthcare system so there are questions
about that as well I would really like
to use applied category Fury for
environmental issues uh but I haven't
quite gotten there yet
anyway sorry I just wanted to emphasize
that uh
you know ethics is the provenance of
philosophers and this is a really
interesting intersection of mathematics
and ethics which I hope that people
think about
and another thing about category three
does is Revitalize what is a very old
question which mathematical structures
are best for describing and designing
systems I emphasize designing because
with the
rise of computers whatever you can think
about clearly enough you can make so
it's not merely describing the external
world it's you're also making worlds
based on your descriptions and so this
immense Freedom that you have in
computer science that the question is
what's what should guide you and it
opens progress it opens possibilities
for some really radical progress because
these are some really brand new ideas
that we're talking about here that may
let us organize systems in new ways
so I think there's a lot to think about
here and I hope
I hope some people here uh give it a try
okay I think I'll
declare it done
brilliant
you can see why I got drawn in by him 30
years ago it's uh
his ways of conveying ideas so clearly
okay um do
let's have some some questions then
um
let me bring up the
people perhaps if people online have
some questions they'd they can raise a
hand and I
perhaps we should be able to see
or anyone here
uh okay uh Mark's but I I do have a
question and I'm I
I'm finding stuff that I've thanks for
that by the way
um this is really exciting stuff for me
but I'm wondering if I'm biased and
reading too much into this that uh uh
that just works in my self-interest
um I do philosophy of time and um I'm
one of the uh the few people who defend
the notion that time flows and uh
um I see in your work uh but I'm uh
maybe it's through these biased eyes
that uh this uh this project is bringing
back the idea of uh of thinking of uh uh
differential equations for instance as
things that flow uh that functions or
something that flow and I noticed the
importance of diagrams as uh and these
diagrams of uh uh uh are reminiscent of
what organizations would call flow
charts and uh um I'm I I'm wondering
whether I'm reading too much into this
as something that might be an answer to
the the static view of uh of uh in in in
maths that came out of uh set theory and
uh uh um thinking of uh um functions as
uh as something that uh is static and
not doesn't float so I'm I'm wondering
whether or not I'm reading too much into
it so maybe maybe that's the question
sure
um yeah the question of static versus
Dynamic is as you know very well or
extremely tricky question because I
could take any dynamical system and
when it's when it's done or when we
imagine it as being
laid out in time then we can think of it
as a static thing with time is just
another space like Dimension and and I
think there's three
it's very hard to like definitively
break out of that uh so but nonetheless
category theory is a generalization of
set theory in a sense in which instead
of just having elements in a set you
have objects and also morphisms and the
morphisms have are meant to convey some
kind of dynamic
that aspect of the system that is a
amorphism goes from an object to an
object and that's a very primitive sense
of Dynamics there of the the start and
the end and and and it brings a kind of
dynamical quality to to the foundations
of mathematics which is is a real thing
it's not it's not just an illusion uh I
mean even though you could if you ask a
traditional mathematician what is a
category and there's a oh it's a set of
objects and a set of morphisms and some
functions doing this and that right so
you could say oh or just back in the
same old Paradigm and that's what I
meant by it's hard to definitively break
out of that Paradigm I I think it's more
in some ways more of a question of
attitude rather than than anything else
uh
and anyway I think the interesting thing
about the differential equations here
may be the interesting new thing maybe
the study of open differential equations
which are differential equations where
some quantities are explicitly labeled
as
affected by the outside world affected
by the part of the world which is not
modeled by the differential equation so
uh traditional differential equations
well no physics often likes to study
what are called autonomous systems of
differential equations where
you know everything there is to know
once you know the differential equations
uh where as open differential equations
which I should say are also studied by
persistent especially Engineers have
certain quantities which are not
determined by the differential equation
they're regarded as being
affected by the outside world and and
that that on the one hand allows you to
treat systems differential equations as
morphisms that it could stick together
by sticking some of these
quantities on the edge to some other
quantities on the edge but it also means
that you're you're not just dealing with
a deterministic system in the classic
sense anymore because you have
quantities that are affected by the
unknown so so they it definitely changes
your attitude towards differential
equations
thanks uh a question from Toby
it's not so much a question sorry
although I would love to I mean there's
lots of Expressions I could ask but I
need to head off because I actually have
to go give this talk again just now
thank you very much for inviting me and
uh I hope the discussion is profitable
okay thanks baby
uh I had a um I was telling the
interests a lot of people around here is
is the difference between when you get
variables that are just sort of
associated with each other there's some
kind of statistical Association versus
when you think there's some kind of
causal connection between them
uh and you might think you might think
you can go much better grip on the world
if it isn't just Association data but
there's a you've got a you know that a
causes B
other ways of getting at this through
your
um or is it is it that you you I guess
the model is a kind of coming already
with their sense of what causes wild and
is there any way of representing the
difference
yeah so this particular
line of work that I was outlining as you
say
I was mainly most of my talk was about
model building where you you have your
opinion about what causes what and how
it
affect what how X affects Y and you
build the model into that so there's a
flip side of the whole um modeling
process which I didn't talk about at all
which is incredibly important in
epidemiology which is
you know inference so you you measure
data and you try to establish
causality and also you know various
numerical
quantities which you would then put into
your model
um so
so there's a lot to applied category
theory has to offer to that and I'm
afraid I'm not quite as uh knowledgeable
about that I will say that
um Brendan Fong for his master's thesis
uh worked on a categorical approach to
uh Bayesian networks and so and and and
that is subsequently grown into things
like what uh Toby was discussing
uh and so that should that's that's also
part of the big story and another part
of it is that
there's a technique called
uh particle filtering
where you which is widely used by
epidemiologists where once you have one
of your models of the sort that I've
been discussing
you run it and you run it a bunch of
times and you see what kind of outcomes
it predicts but then you use that to uh
to compare to reality and you use that
to estimate the parameters that you'd be
in your model
so so I guess what you could say is that
like what I've been describing was just
sort of one half of a feedback loop of
interaction between modeling and then
comparing model with reality and and
yeah so the whole thing should be should
be carefully understood and I'm afraid I
have sort of focused on one half of it
sure yeah I've seen various diagrammatic
techniques from category theorists and
really get it kind of causal modeling I
mean that exists out there doesn't it
yeah it does and that's important
okay um
well there's I think there's no further
questions when we reached six o'clock
anyway so let's just oh sorry was there
one there was a one sorry there's
Dominos yes sorry I I I'm casting around
I have lots of things to say sort of
trying to formulate them into the
questions typical hi John uh
um so one thing that in um I know in
computer science is quite a big deal is
sort of algorithms and data structures
um and kind of getting the right data
structure for the right task to get good
performance
um and
I think you know there's a lot of things
that category theory has to say about
this um
uh kind of describing data structures in
in a more abstract way sort of
polynomial functions and things like
this
um so
what I haven't quite sort of understood
is how much of that kind of work is
going on in in the applied category sort
of movement recently sort of linking
with
with back back with computer science the
sort of like programming aspects around
what I would call kind of classical
computer science of algorithms and data
structures
um do you know if there's much of much
of that going on within the sort of act
World
um or is that
um largely more back with the compute
scientists
um so the algebraic Julia Community is
really trying to
blend
uh
computer programming with category
theory in a really rich way so that you
can write software and you can say you
know Define functor define pre-shift
category blood so that that and that's
just one of several different
initiatives to try to
bring category Theory into programming
so not just have it help programming it
but I would actually be part of the
programming so that that's one thing
there are lots of other things and I
probably don't know the other things so
I will just mention again this company
uh connexus.ai uses uh categorical
approach to databases so it turns out
that the updating databases is very
nicely described using
uh
categorical ideas like on extensions and
um Mike Johnson in Australia has been
serving as a consultant for uh for
database companies using category Theory
ideas uh for many years but now this
company based on David spivex work is is
also doing that
uh and there are and there are a lot of
other things I should say that there's
just
a lot more on the computer science side
that I'm not very familiar with
okay all right okay thank you very much
okay so well here we've reached home so
let's all we have to do is thank John
very much for his for his very
interesting talk
[Applause]
so I've recorded the session and we can
uh
you said you're thinking putting it
online we could yeah I'd like to if
that's acceptable trip yeah yeah let's
do that good all right okay well thanks
thanks ever so much John okay thanks
very much
bye bye everyone online bye I'll see you
see you look like
[Music]
all right